this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for software engineering radio and I'm
here today with Moshe party he's a
professor of computer science at Rice
University and also the director of the
Ken Kennedy Institute for information
technology his interest focus on
applications of logic to computer
science including databases multi-agent
systems verification and reasoning and
on how to teach logic across the
curriculum
welcome to the show machine thank you
it's good to be here I just listened to
a great keynote you gave at exede
International Conference on software
engineering and I'm going to ask you a
few questions today about what we
covered this morning in the keynote
please do the first thing that you
talked about this morning was this
intriguing problem we have in computer
science called P versus NP I heard it's
such an important open question that if
you can solve it you get 1 million
dollars so that seems really exciting
how do I get those million dollars
can you explain through you what exactly
P versus NP means P versus NP is a
question theoretical computer science is
now also accept to be a major problem in
mathematics and the basic intuition
there is actually very very simple if
you think through when you're in high
school and you have to solve a maybe
linear equations and you had to learn
how to solve linear equations and you
came up with a solution and the teacher
would look at your solution and
vertically go tell you correct not
correct without solving the de Polan
ourselves and how did the teacher do it
what you had to do is to plug your
answers into the equations and see
whether it works out or not so this is
checking solution so finding solution
seemed to us intuitively harder than
checking solutions and in fact there are
many many many problems where it's
fairly easy to check solutions
in fact our very language assumed that
finding solution is how a checking is
easy when we talk finding a needle in
the haystack
nobody talks about checking that the
needle is indeed there it's obvious that
if once somebody pointed a needle you
can check that it's there and so we have
this intuition that solving problem is
difficult but checking should be
typically easier and we have many many
many problems we can formally show who
can check solutions efficiently and
these problems are called NP the acronym
itself has a history let's ignore it but
it's called NP NP important that can be
solution can be checked efficiently now
there are fewer problems where we know
how to solve them efficiently so linear
equations is an interesting example
because we know how to solve them
efficiently you were taught an algorithm
in high school called Gaussian
elimination and it's an algorithm with
enable you to solve efficiently linear
equations there are many problems we do
not have yet efficient algorithm for
example the pollen of Hamiltonian cycle
given a graph and network which is a set
of nodes and a set of edges between them
you can take of transportation network
or the cold graph or fill of a drug
large program is all define networks and
the questions can it does a given
network every Hamiltonian cycle we don't
know how to fit how to do that
efficiently it's a major major open
problem but Alain somebody gives you a
candidate solution I think this is
Hamiltonian cycle you can check because
what are the rules has to be a cycle
which mean has to start and finish at
the same node each transition has to be
of an existing edge in the graph and you
cannot visit every node more than once
these are easy to check so it can check
solutions efficiently can we find
solution can we solve the problem
efficiently we don't know that and this
is the question what NP where NP is
about you ask checking there so solving
our intuition says that checking is
easier than solving we have no formal
proof of that and it's conceivable that
we are only edition
misleading us maybe there is a magical
way to turn every checking algorithm
somehow into a solving it so are we
getting close
not really there is a German phrase
maybe there's a similar Dutch phrase
Bench planning got lucky
meant plans and God laughs this problem
is laughing at us it's now open since
the early 70s so we are now about 44 71
I think so 46 we're going to celebrate a
few years the 50th anniversary of the
problem we are not one bit closer to its
solutions that were aware fifty years
ago however you mentioned this morning
that there's also some good news because
it's not hard to solve P versus NP in
the sense that we only need one solution
to eradicate the question once and for
all so can you explain how that works
why do we need to only solve one so so
one of the things that we have we have
it's unfair to say we're not closer with
the Turanian understood much better we
don't know whether linear okto solution
but we have a much deeper understanding
of the what we call where the whole
theory is called computational
complexity theory and the fundamental
concept are now very very clear to us in
a way that they were not you have to
remember bit in the in the 50s and 60s
people tried to address this problem
that seemingly on the face of it the
only way to solve it will require
exhaustive search the only way we just
to keep trying different cycles in in a
in a graph until find a mentorian cycle
and and then for 20 years 50 60 no
progress was made and the big progress
in the in the early 70s was one in this
elucidation between checking in solving
that's one thing and secondly is the
inner we can understand the certain
problems are called np-complete and what
that means that in this class NP the
class of form that can be checked in
polynomial time
which means efficiently these are the
hardest problem
and Hamiltonian cycle is such a problem
and the Traveling Salesman is also such
a problem and what we know what all
these problem that in some sense that
are equivalent to each other if you can
solve on the other one is single one
either by now we have thousands of such
problem you think we have lost count the
earliest people would come there was a
taxonomy and then by the 80s people said
well it just like a zoo we can't keep
type of it anymore
so we don't know how many people but the
estimate is thousands of np-complete
problems in fact by the this theory will
develop in the early seventies by the
time I was a PhD student around 1980 and
I tried to submit a paper saying the
certain problem is np-complete and it
was rejected this is not publishable it
it's boring everybody yeah it's not it
just yeah I would be support but this is
life but all this opponent are
np-complete and one of them is boolean
satisfiability which we'll get to in a
few minutes all of them are formally
equivalent in the sense we kind of solve
one efficiently looking efficient and
that means that in principle if you
resolve one of them we showed that one
of them isn't is in polynomial time it
can be so efficiently all of them are be
sold efficiently and so people usually
focus on some point seem to be more
attractive than others for example I
mean tonin cycles into the very popular
problem and people have published in
quartz alleged poly no matter our
algorithms for this all of them were all
but if somebody is interested they can
go and Google and they can find a nice
websites let's summarize all the proofs
that have been published so far all
along so far P is equal to NP and all
the poor he published of valid P is
different than anything okay we'll make
sure that there that's in the show notes
we have a list of links we can do it so
we will make sure you can read all the
proofs after the podcast if you want to
in 2010 and in HP researcher by the name
of Darrel Ali Cobb announced a big
proved piece difference an entry
and it was people Lucas is formatted in
lattic so it must be serious not like
you know in technical paper is for money
in world we are suspecting me okay but
logic so so it looks credible he was a
principal research at HP Labs so there
was the veneer of respectability so
people took it seriously I was very
excited so he claimed at least he has
opposed the piece differ than NP and he
was using a theorem that I proved many
years ago when I was a postdoc and so I
was excited
maybe my theorem will be used to prove
this but the post collapse within about
he is not 15 minutes of fame but 15 days
of fame before the post completely
collapse someone finally found the
flaw there was a big flaw so yeah so
important attacked a lot of attention
recently a few years ago somebody said
the solution would line some in
algebraic geometry a very deep
mathematical field that most of us know
nothing about most of us don't plan to
study so so far nothing has happened so
and there were values attempt over the
years people camera was this is the
promising direction here's a promising
direction and each time there was a
promising direction so a few years there
is some excitement everybody sign is
promising direction before the realize
it's a mirage we're not making progress
and even though there's no proof most
people assume that the is not equal to
NP what would happen if P turn out to be
equal to NP so I have to say that why
this is a prevailing wisdom a I declare
myself is an agnostic first of all I
said I don't I don't have the this deep
conviction that other people have while
some other people I don't close you know
knows I mean who can you know
this is probably they may be the
greatest computer scientists alive or
one of the few craters are a few people
in this in this caliber and here's on
record he believed the P equal NP and
one reason also is because one thing
that we have discovered in the 80s that
certain problem can be proven to be
solved efficiently
demonstrate in the algorithm so
typically we think that if I want to
show you that a certain problem can be
solved efficiently I have to show you an
efficient algorithm but but people show
that there there are certain post
technique they saw the certain problem
that an algorithm exists without
actually exhibiting the algorithm and so
that means that we might even be able to
show that P equal and P and it will give
us nothing is so frustrating immensely
frustrating all we will have is to exist
an abstract posted something again
algorithm exists we will not be able to
lay out what it is
so one thing we already talked about
that a little bit is sought solving this
is one of those problems in that is
np-complete why is this such a special
why are people focusing on baseball so
one one is is history the history is
that it's a in some cities almost the
beginning of so logic isn't very old
field was big tourist or tell and and
give a lot you come in as long is to be
but in the middle of the nineteenth
century George Boole formalizes it we
have now boolean algebra and so now it's
suddenly moved from philosophy to
mathematical logic and in the middle of
the 19th century people realize it is
such a simple problem it is reasoning
about to enforce yeah because maybe it's
a good idea for our listeners to explain
what exactly do in satisfiability is so
boolean logic is a very very looks is
very simple logic is a logic of to and
force this is it two truth values
nothing more everything is true or false
and then we can combine things we know
that not true is false and not false is
true we know that two and two is true
but true and false is false we know that
true or false is true but false or false
is false these are very simple rules and
these are things people use in
programming your ID condition people use
this thing all the time we use we use
the end and the own they're not
the time this is you cannot think of any
conditions if you don't have the ability
to combine these are the basic combined
effect we know that you don't need any
more than end or and not to do create
any boolean function not to mention the
people who being Hardware every logical
share good it's using no geez boolean
logic in fact when we talked about input
wind electrical engineer talk about
logic its boolean logic they have in
mark
so it's incremental logic and we would
like they to reason about it and one
simple question if you're given the
problem in a symbolic way that is you
have variable the same for 0 or 1 2 or
false and they'll combine using and or
and not the question is is there a way
for this expression to form one can
think of it in a very simple way when
you write a conditional your intention
is the dish we should be able to there
should be both outcomes there should be
true outcome and a false outcome it's if
then else you think that both outcomes
are possible but if you add a very
complex expression maybe it's not it's
possible to devote an expression for
example maybe what your world is
something complex but it's really
equivalent to X equal 1 or not X equal 1
and then it's always going to be true or
maybe you want something that again it's
complicated if you don't see it but if
you simplified it the end of the day
it's equivalent to a cenote and so you
never take that balance so kind of one
of the basics honey take we have about
pokemons we want to make sure that every
branch can be taken both ways
listen to be very very simple problem
turns out the only way really we have
how to solve it in principle is by
trying all combinations so this is ok if
we have if I have two variables P and Q
then there are four possibilities you
can make it through a table that's what
you do stable but if they are what
happen if they are of 10 variables when
out are 10 to the 10 to the 10 it's a
thousand possibilities ok maybe it's
doable or if not I can write a program
to do it
what happen if I have 50 variables now
as it turns out you can argue that
people very rarely write in software
this combination of things but now let's
think about I want to know whether a
particular path in the program can be
taken okay so there is a program and
there are many paths that I can execute
and then I want to know for example I
would like to come up with inputs that
cover all the possible bunches of
punching of the program now if you look
across a branch you will have many many
conditions along the way and by the time
it's a long X if it's a long branch you
may have hundreds of variables in that
particular branch now you say wow 100
now I have to check to the hundred
possibilities to to the hundred is about
10 to the 30 so it's about what is it
about a thousand trillion trillion
trillion it's not going to work and this
is one of those NP complete program
problems for which we don't have an
efficient solution but it's easy to
check because if you give me some
assignments for all the variables like a
min I plug it in and I know remember
that a very simple rule right to enforce
his phone snack to overseas to not true
is false so it's very easy to evaluate
it it's very easy to check if you give
me an assignment but on the face of it
finding an assignment seems to require
exhaustive search we don't have anything
better than in principle we talked a
little but but refine is this in
principle in humility but in principle
seem to take exhaustive search so these
problems is is of immense importance in
you know the basic in software your
write software are many many questions
about software can be used to reason and
you give a few examples so damn and I
say this the simplest example is you
want to generate data so one way even if
you want to do a test suite and you want
to make sure that you have a good
coverage you want to have branch
coverage so that means that you're
trying to
make sure that you have data they drive
you into every bunch of the of the
program and then if then else the two to
the two options and so how do you
generate such data so one way to
generate such data is to do symbolic
execution along different paths and
every edge time into symbolically you're
getting expression that you accumulate
along the different assignments and they
in the branches and then you give these
expressions to a constraint solver to a
Sat solver and this will give
you solution and solution is guaranteed
to take you to that particular location
but wait how can the Sat solver do that
because the oh you just told me the only
way we can do this is by checking all
possibilities so then today the amazing
development in particular of the last
twenty years it is going gap between the
seeming difficulty of the problem from
the theoretical point of view it's an
np-complete problem many of us will
educate to think np-complete this okay
we unsolvable there's nothing we can do
give up just lie on your back and
whimper but the reality of the in
particular this is actually good the
history goes back to the early sixties
people have been thinking about it very
hard for a long time we have to remember
in the nineteenth century people says
this is a very very important problem
you know any shoulder german
mathematician said he said the ultimate
problem in mathematics and logic this is
before there were computer and they
would have doing computation by hand on
board they wanted something fast and it
could find anything fast and people have
been looking at it now for in computer
science going back to the first program
was written to do it was fifty five so
we have now over sixty years of deep and
I would say from these 60 years they
fell 3035 years were very very slow I
mean when I was a when I was a young
researcher there was a small group of
people who did that and many other
people almost looked at them in this
name because they were making it slow
progress doable to solve
hundreds of variables which is
non-trivial but still it's way too small
for many many many many practical
problems and the progress was incredibly
slow and people thought why waste your
time it's np-complete how much bonus do
you hope to make was there at one point
one big breakthrough there was a
sequence of breaks what I would say in
particular there would sum to like a few
key ideas that will develop roughly
around between mid 90s 96 to 2000 one
seemed to be kind of a magical period
some of these ideas I guess existed
before and people have repurpose them
for example there is an idea of what's
called big jumping but Johnny mean bit
so Allah seized approaches today I have
a pretty much all the circular saw for
general approach are based on
backtracking search you take the
expression you're trying to solve a
formula we call it also and you choose a
variable and you assign to it your one
and you simplify and you continue to
make assignment and if you're lucky
you'll find a solution and if not you
realize I failed and you backtalk so
this is essentially backtracking
services something simply it's still
trying all possibilities essentially we
know that backtracking search in
principle is trying all possibilities
and we know that the worst case
complexity is going to be they're going
to travel possibility it's going to be
exponential in number of variables and
you know vector T search is very basic
to connected we teach our students
usually in the first or second year
right it's how we solve many many
problem and we know that it doesn't
scale and if you have large number of
variables what people discover is that
you can start to accumulate new ideas
for example one idea was back jumping
but jumping meant that when you
backtrack
means that you made an assignment and
you fail don't don't act reflexively
spend some time analyzing the failure
because it might be that you realize the
reason for the failure which is some
assignment you've made a bit higher
event so jump back to the arrow okay
jump back to the source of the problem
so one of the thing I said in McKee not
many of the ideas many of the heuristics
is
soldering are you mystics for life so
for example even a mistake analyse your
mistake in in learning from your
mistakes in so big hunting is one
example but even more importantly and
this happened this is in 1996
researchers in the university of
michigan realized that when you make a
mistake even though you may have
assigned hundreds of variable it could
very well be that the reason for the
mistake is some small fraction of this
may be only five variable assignment
that's really the reason for the failure
and so you said this particular
assignment to this fighter but I should
not do it again so you want you write
yourself don't make this mistake again
turned out that too you can write in the
in a logical formula don't make this
particular mistake again so you are a
new fan ooh we call it a clause is a
disjunction is to say do not assign X 1
to 2 and X 3 to 4 and X 5 to 2 and if
you edit as a new requirement this is
not a new constraint so not only you
have learned from your mistake
but you write it in the same syntax of
the formula itself so night become part
of your formula so you have changed the
formula now you have the formula plus
all the mistake that you should not
repeat in in fact on big formulas this
became known as conflict driven closed
learning so the conflict means a bet
assignment an assignment is in conflict
with the formula and the clause is this
forbidden forbidden partial assignment
you can call it a closed so CDCl is the
new way we describe this kind of sad
solders because these are soldiers are
they are learning whenever every time
they make a mistake this is mmm mistake
what went wrong let me understand what
went wrong and there is a whole data
section on the supports we will follow
what this what the assignments are doing
and can go back and analyze it we have
something called an implication graph
and it learns about dependence between
these variables so if a is true then we
see that always B also has two
and so with all this graph and that
means now that if the poem was this
assignments of a and B but a implies B
we don't care about B it's enough to
remember that we should never make a 2
because he faced was invisible and so
cdcl is the new is the new vocabulary
the new term that we have for such
soldiers and so this service now are not
only pure soldiers pure self soldiers
because when they layer a learning is
infrared they make new info and they
look they look at the original set of
conditions and the generate new
conditions and do they typically do that
while they're solving or is there also a
process where the cells over could look
at all the clauses and do some inference
before even starting to assign fashion
so there is a whole bunch of other thing
that people have discovered from the
Macauley pre-processing when you get the
formula don't rush
first of all see what kind of off of low
computational effort you can do to
massage your formula in advance for
example let's suppose that a particular
variable kill only once once some of you
see suddenly something that says P
that's it only once so if I decide this
is if if by making it true I don't win I
win anything there's no other reason
anywhere that would say I should not
make it things are complex usually
because sometimes it P appear positively
but sometimes it appealing
in the summer words not be but if people
only positively you can just make it
true I just make it all and I'm done
this is an example of very low cost low
cost assignment in fact when I do this
the formula would simplify so very often
there is you can do a lot of
pre-processing to make the formulas
simple so so people started with this
clause learning there was a big huge
huge breakthrough that came for me
the Michigan and then a few years later
another panic foo
somebody said what is my SATs what we're
doing
I decide to profile it to see where does
the code Spanish time and discover that
that 80% of the time the code will spend
manipulating a certain bookkeeping
operation that look completely trivial
it was considered to be completely
standard non-controversial booking
booking bookkeeping operation and then
they discovered - there - they were
surprised that 80 percent of the time
was just managing this bookkeeping
covered updating counters and say well
wait a minute discount that this is not
supposed to be a computationally heavy
thing so telling out that there was some
counter that had to be kept but they
have to be updated all the time
and so was consuming and almost not of
effort the counter of what can you
explain so the counter is is what
happened is a memory we have we have
constraints and it constrains when you
convert it with one of the
pre-processing we do we would like to
simplify the syntax of the initial
formula so having some completely crazy
formula we have ways to reduce it to so
called conjunctive normal form contact
no more for women it's a conjunction
conjunction is end of these junctions of
all of variable that are either a pure
positively or negatively contracting of
these junctions now what happened if one
of the disjunction has usually would be
P or Q or not R what happen if one of
these junctions they would be called a
degenerative Junction the unit it's a
unit clause it's a special case of a
t-junction contains only a single
variable because it's appears in a
conjunction in everything in a
conjunction must be true so once a
particular disjunction shrinks to a
single variable positive or negative
that variable tells us P must be talking
as before and now we don't have to make
a choice anymore there's no more this
point is choice will be forced on us
yeah the choice that we made for us to
fall and when the choices we made you
meet this okay we'll make this variable
tool when you make it true you go
wherever it appears and you simplify now
you plug in you do constant propagation
you plug the values and simplify the
expression as you do that other clauses
may become to generate closes and you do
it again and this is something does not
require no backtracking on this one so
you can do it very very fast but you
have to keep track in every clause in
every disjunction how many variables I
have because it only works if it's just
a one it only works on this one so you
basically start by having okay you have
ten and in nine then you kept you come
down to one you say jump on it doing
many I'm ready for now what happened if
I do it all this it's called BCP Warren
constant propagation and then I have not
been able to simplify the part of the
formula completely now I have to go back
to making choices and continue the
backtracking search and what happen if
this particular search failed I have to
picked up when I have to backtrack I
also have to undo all these propagation
of the results and in particular I have
to go in update all the counters so
before that I decremented the counters
and now I have to go back in increment
the counter because this was a wrong
choice and turn out that just
incrementing and decrementing the
counters or consuming a tea personal
terrible type and this was they did
something that people have not done
before just profile the damn code
this podcast is supported by atlanticnet
hosting solution provider of healthcare
HIPAA PCI compliance and ad tech if
you're feeling the pain of having
outdated technology call atlanticnet and
get the latest security firewall
intrusion detection backup disaster
recovery and virtualization or if you're
starting a new project are not giving
the results you want from your current
providers atlanticnet can help you
succeed with fully audited solutions in
23 years in business they won't let you
down
visit atlanticnet to learn more it's so
cool it's an LP of our problem and then
let's just do some profiling and you
find something so this is Wow
we have to have a better way of doing
this in particular they wanted to get
rid off of you know it's what it's
wanting to decrement the counter but
because you backtrack a law you don't
want to do it when you go back when you
when you backed up you don't want to
increment account aspects and the cam up
was very ingenious data structure that
it would be hard to explain just whereby
on the radio but it is like it was such
a require an update when we assign
variables but we never have to update it
when we unassigned variable when you
picked up so it saves a lot of time is
to call there is a name is called too
literal watching just keeping two
pointers and we won't go into the
details but then again was a very simple
idea in these two ideas by themselves
that close learning and to literally
watching suddenly the SAS wouldn't start
solving pick a bigger problem in so bite
by 2001 people realized wow something is
happening here this is not the old sad
soldiers and then you start looking at
other you will stick that can come into
the picture
okay so bed jumping was you which didn't
exist before people in concerns that is
in concern solving
came up with it people say let's use it
here very useful they another heuristic
that came up from Princeton was you have
to choose variables
to assign 0 or 1 as you do the
backtracking search each time you have
to say okay what's my next village 1
shall I pick which one shall like people
and people have over the years thought
of more and more sophisticated mystic
circle it's called also a decision
decision your mystic decide which
variable to to assign if people have
come up with more and more sophisticated
eristic why because they want lets they
thought that the goal would be to have a
smaller search tree where with as little
backtracking as possible
people's a better king is bad it's like
to minimize backtrack and the problem
water would do not realize you're
spending more and more time making a
decision so while your search tree was
smaller every node in the circuit was
consuming more and more time and again
the Princeton team says let's relax it a
little bit let's focus on a decision
heuristic that is not too stupid but
equally important is very fast in a came
up with a very good heuristic strike the
balance between how smart it is in how
fast it is and so when we look today
when we compare the search trees of the
new aristocracy the search trees are
bigger but we spend so so much fuel less
time at every node that you have time
life to just try overall although
overall we save time yeah so the key
thing to observe is that the time that
you spend is the side of the tree time
the time that you spend in every node
and even though you won is becoming
bigger the other one is smaller than
small enough you still gain can you give
an estimate of how much speed up we've
acquired in all 30 years how much
quicker have they become so and is so to
answer that questions they a colleague
of mine at Berkeley decide the few years
ago to benchmark 12 years of such
soldiers so he took 12 horses for them
from 2000 to 2012 and he applied them to
the same benchmark over the years they
were
all published in different tables there
are no different machines or different
benchmark he said I'm gonna take 1 2012
machine 1 benchmark and compare 12 years
of such solvers ensured that the polio
was taking 800 seconds in 2000 so
remember mm mm is before the 2001
buttocks wet police tone but after the
1996 breakthrough in Michigan but was
taken 800 seconds in 2000 I was taking
one second 2012 so this this is three
forms of magnitude improvement so we
went from 800 seconds over to one second
just really magnitude in 12 years this
is an astounding astounding progress now
I you know somebody somebody needs to
redo it now to see what it would be now
after no instead of just 12 years 17
years into the comparison but there is
an annual competition so we kind of see
that we are still improving in the
double digit speed every year and nobody
quite understand why are we making such
good progress accepted lots of human
ingenuity is good into it and everybody
hasn't a goal now to go and submit
another entity to the sat competition
and become the champion it's very good
motivator and people talk about Moore's
law for such solvers kind of has a half
joke because we seem to just constantly
making progress every new every area so
it's not sixty percent per year we're
not quite well more lowers but we're
still making double-digit improvement
per year so if we come back to peace MP
maybe it doesn't really matter all that
much
whether or not it's the same because we
make so much progress that after a while
we can solve the MP problems really
quickly even though it's not fully no
real so we have to be careful so the
answer to your question is yes and no so
we know that that is a difficult problem
because once you understand how good
solvers work you can generate how
artificial heart in senses so we can do
they generate instances with few hundred
very
that no one can sold we know that we
know how to do it but these are all
artificial problems there is something
magical about problems that come from
industrial problems formed for example
this as I told you these tools that
Microsoft is using which is to to do
symbolic execution along execution path
collect the conditions solve them and
then get inputs that will derive the
program to this to a particular desired
location or people using more
sophisticated technique model checking
is a technique of doing kind of very
heavy duty static analysis of program to
understand for example I may want to
know in bounded model checking I want to
check that all paths of a certain length
will never reach doing a self regulation
okay so maybe where I can do it as even
some technique how I can do it for
arbitrary length path but all these
techniques are very at the end of the
day they they use such solvers is there
an underlying engines and this problem
somehow to be much much easier then
these artificial instance are gonna call
to generate so it's not as if MP control
as angry have become easy there's
something about it not all of them we
run one cinema one reporter who said
this one we cannot solve but very a very
very large number of polling to come up
for me dazzle applications do not seem
the difficulty and what would you limit
it we today are able to solve problems
sub problems up to 5 million variables
this is family remember that about 25
years ago we are dealing with 500
variables and in this 25 years we made
for 500 variables to 5 so to protect the
possible number of options is 2 to the
power of 5 million it's a number that
does not exist in the universe ok and of
course we are not covering this such a
space no the whole point is that by
we reduce it dramatically using all
these heuristics reduce it very very
dramatically so let's talk a little bit
more about applications we've already
talked about the Microsoft work can you
talk a little bit more about them they
have their own sources so Microsoft has
been a leader therefore formed one is
they have people Microsoft research work
to develop some of the best Sat solver
the heavy two called z3 this hood I
believe is is actually available yes you
can use it other people can use it we
will link to it and they have the whole
suite of tools and again many of these
foods are available
I don't know but specific tool but many
of the tools are available one of the
tool that was developed even before that
but became much better was it with the
development of Sat solver is a tool I
think it's called STV static device very
fire and this is a tool to make sure the
device drivers are complying with the
protocol of the operating system so it
turns out that many time will you get a
fatal failure get like a blue screen
it's really as a result of mismatch
between the device driver and the
portable of the operating system and so
people will blame Microsoft for all this
blue screen the Microsoft said it's on
acid this was the device driver so they
end up developing tools to help people
who I device drivers to to check the
town in compliance with a portable
operating system and that was a problem
that was and be completely stacked one
this is even is even worse an
np-complete is even worse we won't even
go there but the point is that the
despot these advances in SATs although
it's the ablest to make advanced in many
other areas because it is such a
fundamental problem it is reasoning
about zero and one in some sense the
corners the depth the most you can think
of it in the most fundamental
optimization problem just zeros and one
what could be singles in the reason
about zeros and ones where else's no it
used I know this is a soft surface for
software developers but you can imagine
how useful this would be when people
design computer circuits which are
really about zeros zeros and ones and in
fact we'll use it very heavily I mean
companies such as Intel and other
companies they have a whole bunch of
tools to reason about for example here
is a Silkwood and i've optimized it now
using various tools disclose secret
equivalent so I fully trust my tool
maybe I should have another sanity check
to rezone the two tools the two circles
are equivalent I'm asking is there an
input for the two circles will give
different result this is exactly that
this is another instance of such so they
are now able to reason about much bigger
instances as before and again because I
mean SATA is becoming now kind of a
fundamental problem whenever you're
dealing with the discrete space you say
I can use it to set the same way that
many many many logistical problems I
reduce to linear programming that people
are saying is discrete if it's discrete
I cannot reduce it to such how would you
reduce it I need to for that but I need
to I want to do I'm doing register
allocation so inside either Michael my
compiler when I go to the final code
from the intermediate code today to the
low-level code I need to register a
location register allocation has been
known for a while to be equivalent to
some kind of a graph coloring problem
graph coloring we are given a graph and
we the question is how many colors if
you think of it as a map so we don't
want to enable countries having the same
color so the question there is how many
colors do you need to color the graph to
color every node so no two nodes of the
same color are connected by an edge so
in this case the edges represent
dependency between variables anyway to
make sure the variable the dependency
they have to be memory at the same time
are assigned two different registers and
so people have realized that register
locations require absolving graph
coloring problem
which was also an empty complete problem
so they come up with all kind of you
stills but now the answer is it could
very well be that inside the compiler
we're going to have a shot solve them
that will solve this more efficiently
well compiling while compiling because
if it's fast enough you know not maybe
not your every compiler but it is your
optimizing compiler where you are
willing to let it run a bit longer
inside the compiler compiler will call
the Sat solver it would reduce graph
coloring to goodness satisfiability
because after all you know even if we
have more than two colors we can always
reduce everything to bits we know that
everything's finite can be reduced to
beasts and what I certify abilities
reasoning about bits and we know that in
our field at the end there is the bit
the whole bit nothing but the beat okay
so many many problem can be reduced to
satisfiability so we are now in position
to start exploring but not if not all of
this has been done but now watching the
success we've had over the past 25 years
part of my goal here to pour modest is
to tell that and this here at XC there
it is wonderful tool now go explore see
what you can do with it where do you
think it sets over can be explored where
it's not currently what are some of them
where should we go I mean I you know I
go here as I'm here and I go and I look
at some talking for example people talk
about the combinatorial test generation
and it really talks about what happen if
you've done software product line and
there are many many many possible
configurations and you want to generate
data that would cover all this different
configuration and again a way to do this
you will chord all these constraints as
good and constraints you everything is
you reduced even we are talking about
that may be certain option can have
let's say eight values say okay eight
values this is free beats so I think all
eight values by three bits and I can
write all the condition all the
dependencies I can write all of them at
the end is boolean formulas and the for
an hour can give to a Sat solver and ask
for is the resolution or give me
different solutions to cover the
different different configurations so
now it's up to our imagination there is
this wonderful too
any basic can handle large large it can
store large wooden constraints and that
means that many problems that we thought
were beyond our reach and we came up
with what kind of approximate solution
and find a way around it now we can say
you know what let's go for the whole
thing
let's try to solve this problem now
there's no guarantee I said np-complete
steel does not mean easy but it means it
means it's out in the worst case and
worst case is very pessimistic you know
it just could be that yeah once and
while we're going to get stuck but this
is life we don't get everything you want
in life if you get 99% it's still pretty
good
and so I think we have an opportunity
now for this tool that exists and the
tools are getting better every year they
are all available usually they are
available is open source so people can
go and can adapt to their own
application and I think what we need now
is for people kind of to move to the
next level which is just you know think
of what happened for example when people
discover electricity the beginning or
just moving legs or forms right but then
think of what explosion came up with you
realize I can use electricity and all
kinds of ideas that nobody would have
thought before I can have electric car I
can open it you know it's just people
come up with you know imagination or
what can I else like what can I elect
refer this because the electrification
of our economy what if occasion of a of
computer science what else can we do
with it yeah because the applications
you describe are really brought from
test generation to compilers is sort of
the entire spectrum
every place you need to do compete
you're kind of this combinatorial
reasoning its reducible to such remember
that is np-complete so we know that
every problem that is in NP that is can
be checked efficiently can be in
principle reduced to say that it doesn't
always mean that this that the reduction
to Sat is necessarily good way of
solving the problem but it's a it's a
good first attempt you should always try
this in particular because let's suppose
the dirt again your time to solve the
original location
and you can say well but my problem is
special
so I can use I can use special you
wished it for my poll because I know
this is goth coloring and I know other
stuff I said yes you can but the
hundreds of people who every year are
making such well was better do you think
you can compete with these people this
is a little bit they used to be a phrase
it was called courts always win and
Court stood for community off the shelf
and people try to use what kind of a
specialized architecture for this and
for that and all of this effort have
essentially failed because the commodity
processors were getting every year
better and better and better so then
people said the best your best attempt
is just that Intel do it think it's
Intel and mdn would ever do it thing
just use commodity pasta sauce so that's
will continue to improve and therefore
at this point it's a very good fair
strategies first of all let me try to
reduce it to some that it gives me an
appropriate solution because time to
develop my own your way stick about
solvers this is much harder work than
just finding a way to reduce intercept
yeah then you can say you can benefit
from all the advancements that have been
made but also that will be made will be
made to continue to improve every year
they're getting better and better and
better so the same way that you can say
well this problem is too hard but next
year in turn will come up with a new
Porsche solvent now I will be able to do
it now you can say the same thing well
this is still not not good enough I'm
going to another year that's what I will
get better in a year and maybe then it
would be good I know of course it works
double because the sauce always get
better but also the machines get that
she's so the same solver or new hardware
will also improve absolutely so there's
lots of opportunities there lots of
people to apply this problem that is so
old that has been bothering all of us
for so long I think this is a really
very exciting time because I get a
partner that we thought was very hard
turn out to be not so hard in practice
and now we need people to explore and
see what you can do with it the same way
again it another technology whenever we
have a new technology it takes lots of
people trying different things to see
what can you do with this technology
this is a fantastic way to end to show
that there's so much still ahead of us
that we live in exciting times very
exciting times thanks a lot for being on
the show we will make sure that
everything is linked to so the proofs
and also some sulfur so if you really
want to check it out after the show then
you can totally do that thanks a lot
motion for you thanks for listening to
se radio an educational program brought
to you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening